<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sridhar's Blog! – Momentum Trading</title><link>https://ssathya.github.io/SridharBlog/tags/momentum-trading/</link><description>Recent content in Momentum Trading on Sridhar's Blog!</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:20:35 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssathya.github.io/SridharBlog/tags/momentum-trading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Momentum Trading</title><link>https://ssathya.github.io/SridharBlog/posts/momentum-trading/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 00:20:35 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://ssathya.github.io/SridharBlog/posts/momentum-trading/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, momentum investing appears more like a reflexive response to market trends than a deliberate investing strategy. The concept of selling underperforming assets and purchasing those on the rise is enticing, but it directly challenges the timeless Wall Street principle of &amp;ldquo;buy low, sell high.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article explores the concept of momentum investing, examining its advantages and drawbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Richard Driehaus wasn&amp;rsquo;t the pioneer of momentum investing, he refined the approach and implemented it as the cornerstone of his fund management strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He believed that greater profits could be achieved by &amp;ldquo;buying high and selling higher,&amp;rdquo; rather than purchasing undervalued stocks and waiting for the market to recognize their worth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Momentum investing?&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="what-is-momentum-investing"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#what-is-momentum-investing" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Momentum investing capitalizes on market volatility by entering short-term positions in rising stocks and selling them at the first signs of decline. The investor then reallocates the capital to fresh opportunities. In this analogy, market volatility resembles ocean waves, with a momentum investor riding the crest of one wave and swiftly transitioning to the next before the first wave crashes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Momentum investors also exploit the phenomenon of investor herding, positioning themselves at the forefront to profit and exit before the crowd. Below, you&amp;rsquo;ll find a table outlining how momentum investing compares with other popular strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building blocks for Momentum Investing&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="building-blocks-for-momentum-investing"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#building-blocks-for-momentum-investing" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigating momentum markets demands advanced risk management strategies to tackle challenges such as volatility, overcrowding, and unforeseen pitfalls that can erode profits. However, traders often disregard these principles, driven by a deep-seated fear of missing out on rallies or sell-offs while others secure substantial gains. These guidelines can be summarized into five key components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opt for liquid securities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carefully manage risks during trade entries and exits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aim to enter positions early.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select your holding period judiciously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execute your exit with precision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Opt for liquid securities&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="opt-for-liquid-securities"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#opt-for-liquid-securities" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When employing momentum strategies, prioritize liquid securities. Avoid leveraged or inverse ETFs, as their price movements often fail to accurately reflect underlying indices or futures markets due to their intricate construction. While regular funds are reliable trading options, they typically deliver smaller percentage gains and losses compared to individual stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focus on securities with a daily trading dollar volume is high, as many well-known stocks meet this standard. Occasionally, low-float stocks can become highly liquid when significant news breaks, driving heightened volatility and attracting diverse market participants through strong emotional reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep an eye out for the &amp;ldquo;flavor of the day&amp;rdquo;—new products, divisions, or concepts that captivate public interest, compelling analysts to discard traditional models and recalculate profit projections. Biotech firms and small- to mid-sized tech companies are particularly abundant sources of such compelling story stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Carefully manage risks during trade entries and exits&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="carefully-manage-risks-during-trade-entries-and-exits"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#carefully-manage-risks-during-trade-entries-and-exits" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;To ensure the success of a momentum strategy, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to thoroughly address the risk factors involved. Common pitfalls in momentum trading include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entering a position prematurely, before the momentum move is fully confirmed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exiting a position too late, after the market has reached saturation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neglecting to monitor the market, leading to missed shifts in trends, reversals, or unexpected news events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holding a position overnight, exposing it to external influences after market hours that can cause significant price and pattern changes the next day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delaying action on a losing position, inadvertently following the momentum in the wrong direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Managing Your Position&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="managing-your-position"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#managing-your-position" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mastering position management takes practice, as securities well-suited for momentum trades often have wide bid/ask spreads. These spreads require more substantial price movements to generate profits, and the large intraday fluctuations can trigger stop-losses, even if the overall trend remains intact. Carefully select your holding period, as risk escalates with longer positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Securing Profits&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="securing-profits"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#securing-profits" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take profits when the price surges into an overextended technical state. This is often indicated by a sequence of vertical bars on a 60-minute chart or when the price breaches the third or fourth standard deviation of a top or bottom 20-day Bollinger Band.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider tightening stop-losses or executing a blind exit upon reaching key technical levels, such as a major trendline or a previous high/low. Partial profit-taking or exiting altogether is prudent when indicators suggest potential trend reversals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Advantages of Momentum Investing&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="advantages-of-momentum-investing"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#advantages-of-momentum-investing" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Momentum investing can yield significant returns for traders who possess the right temperament, can manage the associated risks, and remain committed to the strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Short-Term High Profit Potential:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="short-term-high-profit-potential"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#short-term-high-profit-potential" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Momentum investing offers the chance for substantial gains over short periods. For example, buying a stock at $50 and selling at $75 based on an overoptimistic analyst report could generate a 50% return before the stock corrects. Over time, the cumulative profit potential can be immense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exploiting Market Volatility:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="exploiting-market-volatility"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#exploiting-market-volatility" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Momentum investors thrive on volatile market trends, targeting stocks on the rise and selling before prices decline. Staying ahead of the curve allows for maximum return on investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Capitalizing on Emotional Market Behavior:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="capitalizing-on-emotional-market-behavior"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#capitalizing-on-emotional-market-behavior" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of being swayed by emotions like many investors, momentum traders profit from price changes driven by emotional decisions, relying on discipline and predefined entry and exit points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Disadvantages of Momentum Investing&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="disadvantages-of-momentum-investing"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#disadvantages-of-momentum-investing" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, momentum investing comes with its challenges, as the risk-return trade-off inherent to all strategies applies here as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Risk of Poor Timing:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="risk-of-poor-timing"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#risk-of-poor-timing" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like riding ocean waves, a mistimed purchase can leave an investor stranded. Most momentum traders accept this risk in pursuit of higher returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;High Turnover Costs:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="high-turnover-costs"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#high-turnover-costs" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Frequent trading can lead to substantial fees, which remain a concern for new investors despite low-cost brokerage options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Time-Intensive Approach:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="time-intensive-approach"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#time-intensive-approach" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Momentum investing requires constant monitoring of market updates, often on a daily or hourly basis, to quickly respond to news or trends that could influence stock prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Market Sensitivity:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="market-sensitivity"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#market-sensitivity" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Momentum strategies are more effective in bull markets, where investor herding behavior is more pronounced. In bear markets, increased caution among investors reduces profit margins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;ETFs&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="etfs"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#etfs" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are several alternatives that enable retail investors to access momentum strategies without requiring hands-on management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Momentum ETFs:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="momentum-etfs"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#momentum-etfs" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Passive Solution Momentum-focused ETFs apply rules-based methodologies to identify and invest in stocks with strong price momentum, effectively streamlining and automating the momentum investment approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/trading/introduction-to-momentum-trading/#toc-5-exiting-with-profits"target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Investopedia&lt;/a&gt; has built a chart listing some of the ETFs that people can consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Symbol&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MTUM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tracks an index of large/mid cap U.S. stocks with higher price momentum.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MMTM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The fund invests at least 80% of its assets in the index, which reweights the S&amp;amp;P Composite 1500 Index to overweight stocks with strong momentum and underweight those with weak momentum. The fund is non-diversified.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;PDP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The fund invests at least 90% of its assets in the underlying index, which includes about 100 securities selected from the largest 1,000 by market capitalization in the NASDAQ U.S. benchmark index.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;SPMO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The fund invests at least 90% of its assets in the underlying index, which includes around 100 S&amp;amp;P 500® stocks with the highest &amp;ldquo;momentum score.&amp;rdquo; Momentum investing focuses on securities with strong recent performance. The fund is non-diversified.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend SPMO!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>